Phillip: Poor communication has a wide
range of negative effects for all types
of workplaces, so let’s look at some
of the possible impacts in detail.
Maddy: Damage to timelines
If there is ineffective communication
in the workplace, people won’t
know what the deadlines are.
These can lead to increased time pressures and
possibly sloppy work, as people race to hit
deadlines, or deadlines are missed altogether.
This will almost always have a knock-on effect.
Say, for example, due to poor communication,
someone in the IT department of a company
is under the impression, that a new system
doesn’t need to be put in place for a month.
They then learn it is business critical and
must be finished before the end of the week!
Even if it is completed on time, it’s more than
likely it will not be executed to a good standard.
And the person working on it, will
have experienced unnecessary stress
and anxiety and felt highly pressured.
Phillip: Reduced productivity
As poor communication is likely to mean
that people don’t always know what they’re
expected to be doing, some may put their
energy and resources into the wrong places.
They might start work on something
that’s being worked on by someone
else or has already been completed.
They may misunderstand a business need and create
something that doesn’t meet the goals and targets.
They may even think that there’s nothing to do
that day, because no one’s told them otherwise!
Maddy: Competing communication styles
Although everyone has their preferred
method of communication, and that’s fine!
- there does still need to be some common
understanding throughout a workplace,
about how people should communicate.
People need to know what channels to use,
and the tone of voice they’re expected to
use in written and spoken communication
especially with customers, and such.
Without this, you’ll find that people just use
whatever channel or style they prefer, which
may not be the most suitable or efficient one.
For example, a manager who hates to use
phone or video calls, only communicates
via emails and instant messaging.
This might lead his team to feel very distant from
him, like he isn’t in the loop and doesn’t care.
This will then be bad for their morale.
Phillip: Lack of engagement and lowered wellbeing
Poor communication may also mean
that people don’t feel like they
belong to their team or organization.
They’ll feel isolated, lonely, and
their morale will be low, so causing an
impact on productivity and retention.
Maddy: Closed minds
Without open and effective lines of communication
between people and teams, employees won’t be
regularly exposed to new ideas and approaches.
This can mean that inefficient methods don’t get
corrected and that problems don’t get solved.
Phillip: Poor retention
Without effective communication helping
people to feel like they’re a part of
their organization, there will be a reduced
desire to be loyal to their employer.
They won’t feel like their contributions are
being noticed or their ambitions respected.
This means it will be much harder to retain
talent and time and money will be spent having to
hire new employees, to replace the ones who go,
possibly starting the whole process over again.
Maddy: Ineffective or poor communication in the
workplace can be frustrating at all levels and
can create a breeding ground for mistrust and
confusion and help create stressed employees.
It also makes it difficult for people to
work together closely, collaboratively,
and successfully as a team.
This can then impact greatly on the
success of the business or organization
overall, lowering morale and motivation and
ultimately affecting a businesses reputation.